Finding Aid for David Giltrow photograph collection, 1960-1961
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David Giltrow photograph collection 1960-1961
Giltrow, David
0.2 linear feet
2013124 Aa 2
David Giltrow was a student photographer for The Michigan Daily and Michiganensian from 1960 to 1961. The collection contains negatives and paper contact prints of photos taken by Giltrow. Subjects include John F. Kennedy's 1960 campaign stop in Ann Arbor and whistle stop train trip in Michigan, campus visits by Pat Kennedy Lawford and Chester Bowles, a Pete Seeger concert, Americans Committed to World Responsibility Conference, and a 1961 Ann Arbor Civil Rights march.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
by David Giltrow (Donor 10261 ) in October 2013.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open without restriction
David Giltrow graduated from the University of Michigan in 1961. While a student, Giltrow worked as a photographer for the campus newspaper The Michigan Daily and the Michiganensian yearbook. He photographed the 1960 John F. Kennedy and Richard Nixon presidential campaigns for the Michigan Daily. Upon graduation he joined the American Friends Service Committee as a volunteer in Tanzania, arriving just ahead of the first recruited Peace Corps group of civil engineers. Giltrow was assigned to the government film unit. Following his three year assignment, Giltrow enrolled at Syracuse University where he received a master's degree and Ph.D. degree in instructional technology. At Syracuse he served as a program assistant in Syracuse's Peace Corps training programs for Africans in the 1960s. Returning to Tanzania in 1969, he researched young Tanzanians' comprehension of motion picture elements. During this time he met Peggy Medina who was completing two years as a volunteer. Medina returned to Michigan to work on a library degree at the University of Michigan. They were married in Ann Arbor in 1971 when Giltrow returned to the United States.
After completing his doctorate, Giltrow went on to work in some 20 developing countries in Africa, Southeast Asia and the Middle East as an independent consultant in distance education, agricultural communications, community forestry and development projects for the United Nations, World Bank, and USAID.
The David Giltrow photograph collection documents a selection of Giltrow's work as a photographer for the Michigan Daily and the Michiganensian from 1960 to 1961. The collection consists of original 35mm negatives and paper contact prints. The negatives cover six notable campus visitors and events. The collection also contains a brief biography and a group portrait of Michiganensian photographers which includes Giltrow.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; Giltrow, David.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Seeger, Pete, 1919-; African Americans--Civil Rights.; Americans Committed to World Responsibility at the University of Michigan.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Kalamazoo (Mich.); Michigan daily.; Political elections--1960.; Political parades and rallies.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biography
  Biography contains a brief biographical sketch of Giltrow's career.
  - Brief biography by Giltrow (Box 1)
- Portraits
  Portraits contains a portrait of Giltrow in the 1960s and a group photograph of the 1960 Michiganensian photographers which includes Giltrow and Fred Shippey along with David Newman, Mike Factor, Paul Krynicki, and Gerry Aronheim.
  - Print of Michiganensian photographers, 1960 (Box 1)
- Pat Kennedy Lawford
  Pat Kennedy Lawford negatives documents the campus visit of Pat Kennedy Lawford, the sister of John F. Kennedy. Lawford visited Ann Arbor and met with supporters in the Michigan Union. G. Mennen Williams, the Governor of Michigan also spoke at the Michigan Union during the event.
  - Negatives of visit, October 1960 (Box 1)
- John F. Kennedy Whistle Stop Tour of Michigan
  John F. Kennedy Whistle Stop Tour of Michigan includes negatives taken by Giltrow while covering Kennedy's campaign visit to Michigan for the Michigan Daily. Giltrow traveled with Kennedy's entourage of photographers and journalists on the whistle stop tour which was to travel through Jackson, Albion, Battle Creek, Kalamazoo and Grand Rapids before finishing at Lansing. This was reportedly the only whistle stop train tour of Kennedy's campaign. Michigan Governor G. Mennen Williams
  Kennedy flew to Michigan following the televised debate with Richard M. Nixon, and landed at Willow Run Airport on October 13, 1960. Kennedy eventually made his way to the Michigan Union after midnight where he was greeted by thousands of students and supporters prompting an impromptu speech on the steps of the Union where he introduced the idea of the Peace Corps. On October 14, Kennedy left the Union and embarked on a train trip across Michigan. The negatives document Kennedy's speech at the Michigan Union, the crowd awaiting Kennedy, and his departure later that morning.
  Several negatives of the whistle stop train trip document campaign stops in Grand Rapids and Kalamazoo. A reproduction of Kennedy's Michigan itinerary is included. It details times and anticipated schedules for Kennedy and his entourage.
  - Negatives of campaign stops, October 1960 (Box 1)
- Chester Bowles
  Chester Bowles October 1960 visit to the University of Michigan is recorded in negatives of his presentation at the Michigan Union. Speaking on world affairs, Bowles was John F. Kennedy's foreign policy advisor. Bowles speech reportedly influenced Al and Judy Guskin who started a Peace Corps group at Michigan.
  - Negatives of visit, October 1960 (Box 1)
- Pete Seeger
  Pete Seeger Concert negatives show Seeger performing in the Winter of 1961 at Ann Arbor High School.
  - Negatives of concert at Ann Arbor High School, 1961 (Box 1)
- Americans Committed to World Responsibility Conference
  Negatives of the March 1961 Americans Committed to World Responsibility Conference show Michigan Daily editor Tom Hayden, Daily night editor Phil Power and Sharon Jeffries, daughter of Democratic leader Millie Jeffries at the conference along with speakers Sargent Shriver and Hubert H. Humphrey. Henry Reuss, co-sponsor with Humphrey of Peace Corps type legislation, also spoke at the conference.
  - Negatives of Conference, March 1961 (Box 1)
- Ann Arbor Civil Rights March
  Ann Arbor Civil Rights March negatives show a march and demonstration for Civil Rights in April 1961. The march was down State Street with speeches on the University of Michigan diag. Roger Seasonwein was the organizer for the march.
  - Negatives of March, April 1961 (Box 1)
Related Material
Additional photographs from the same era may be found in the Michigan Daily records also held by the Bentley Historical Library. The Frederick L. Shippey visual materials collection features the work of another Michigan Daily photographer covering the Kennedy campaign stop in Michigan. The Samuel F. Schneider photograph collection contains 15 prints of the Kennedy visit to Ann Arbor taken by Schneider, an independent photographer.